（デスラー）この星にしがみついて
なんになる？
What point is there in clinging to this planet?
We'll be entering atmosphere shortly. Please return inside.
（フラーケン・通信）
間もなく　大気圏に入ります。→
艦内に　お戻りください。
ガチャ（扉の音）
（ギムレー）ゼーリックに同調した
反乱分子は→
My secret police have already found all subversive elements allied with Zoellick.
すでに
我が秘密警察が　内定済みです。
（セレステラ）
間もなく　一掃できるでしょう。
We'll be able to wipe them out before long.
君には
不愉快な思いをさせてしまった。
I'm sorry for what I put you through.
Not at all, sir.
（ドメル）いえ…。
（ヒス）しかし→
But now your rule is secure.
これで　総統の治世も
盤石というものです。
主力艦隊を　９０日のかなたに
置き去りにしたというのにかね？
Despite the fact that I left the main fleet ninety days away?
はっ…　そ　それは…。
Oh! Well...
I'm told they will take a minimum of three months to return to the Home Planet?
本国に戻るには
最低でも　３か月を要するとか。
Balun is the center of the Geschtam Gates comprising the hyperspace navigation network.
（ガデル）バランは
ゲシュタムの門で構成される→
超航法ネットワークの
中枢だ。→
それを破壊されたため→
Its destruction means that most of the primary fleets remain here.
我々の基幹艦隊の大半は
まだ　この宙域だ。
んん…。
（ガデル）つまり→
In other words, it is now impossible
通常のゲシュタム航法だけでは
基幹艦隊が→
for our primary fleets to reach the Yamato via normal Geschtam navigation.
ヤマトに追いつくことは　もはや→
不可能ということだ。
総統。→
My lord...
ひと言　お命じください→
Issue the order to sink the Yamato.
ヤマトを沈めよと。
やってくれるかね？
Would you do it?
一命に代えて。
At the cost of my life.
We've prepared the best crew for you.
お前のために精鋭を取りそろえた。
首尾よく　ヤマトを沈めた暁には→
Should you defeat the Yamato, your wife's punishment will be reduced.
奥方も
罪一等を減じられるであろう。
I am grateful, Deputy Lord Hyss.
ご配慮　感謝します　ヒス副総統。
Elk, I have one more request...
エルク…　君には　もう一つ→
Just for you.
頼みがある。
（玲）病室　抜け出して…。→
You left the medical room. Makoto was looking for you.
真琴が捜してたよ。
（篠原）お前
あそこから飛び立ってんのな。
So that's where you take off from, huh?
（篠原）
で？　連れ戻しに来たってわけ？
Well? Did you come to retrieve me?
ふふっ　そんなとこ。
Something like that.
Shinohara, you were in my brother Akio's squad, weren't you?
篠原　確かあんた→
明生兄さんと
一緒の部隊だったんだよね？
（篠原）ああ。　いいヤツだった。
Yeah, he was a good man.
Sword 3 was his code name.
「ソードスリー」って
兄さんのコードネームだったんだ。
あっ…。　ははっ　そっか。
I see...
あいつ
そういうの話さないからな。
He never discussed that stuff.
そういうヤツでした。
That's the kind of guy he was.
そういうヤツだった。
We've made it to the Large Magellanic Cloud, haven't we?
（玲）私たち
大マゼランまで来たんだよね。
（篠原）ああ。　来たんだ。
Yes, we have.
Congratulations.
（新見・通信）おめでとう。
あなたが正しかったわけね。→
You were right. I never expected we'd ever get this far.
ほんとに
ここまで来られるなんて…。
（島・通信）
正しいとか正しくないとか→
I don't know if "right" is the way I'd put it.
そりゃあ
いろいろあるだろうけど→
But there is only one reality.
事実は　一つだけさ。
僕たちは　ここまで来たんだ。
And the reality is that we made it.
What are you looking at?
（星名）何を見ているんです？
（百合亜）星を…。
The stars.
The Tarantula Nebula? Impressive, isn't it?
（星名）タランチュラ星雲か。
きれいですよね。
（百合亜）あの向こうに
イスカンダルがあるの。
Beyond it lies Iscandar.
一緒に帰りたかった…
サーシャ姉様と。
I wanted to come home with Sasha.
（星名）ユリーシャ…。　えっ!?→
Yurisha...
あっ…　ああっ！　はぁ…→
危ないじゃないですか。
ごめんね　星名。
That's dangerous.
I'm sorry, Hoshina.
Yuria says she wants you to hug her.
百合亜は　早く　あなたに→
ギュッてしてほしいって
言っている。
（星名）えっ？
「ギュッ」て　何？
What is a hug?
An Iscandarian on board the Yamato?
（ハイデルン）
ヤマトに　イスカンダルの方が？→
信じられませんな。
Unbelievable.
（ドメル）バランに
セレステラが来たことがあったろ。
Remember when Cerestella went to Balun?
（ハイデルン）確か
アケーリアス遺跡の調査で…　でしたな。
She was investigating the Aquarius ruins, yes?
あのとき　遺跡を利用して
ヤマトの情報を入手したようだ。
She used the ruins to retrieve information on the Yamato.
（ハイデルン）まさか
そんなことが…。
I didn't know that was even possible!
She is a witch, after all.
あの女は　魔女だからな。
おかげで
任務が　１つ増えたというわけだ。
And so, I have another mission now.
（バレク）着陸する。　接舷準備！
We're landing. Prepare to disembark!
（ハイデルン）やれやれ…。
子供と年寄りばかりか。
Nothing but children and old men, huh?
（ドメル）精鋭が聞いてあきれるな。
"The best crew," right?
（バーガー）
ったく…　空母が　４杯だけかよ。
Only four carriers?
（クライツェ）ぼやくな　バーガー。
No complaints, Berger.
The Imperial Guard controls the Homeland Defense Fleets.
（ゲットー）本土防衛艦隊は
親衛隊のヤツらが→
牛耳っている。
こちらには回ってこない。
They won't give us more.
（バーガー）へいへい。
おっ？　バーレン！
Barlen!
（バーレン）おお～　ハイデルンか。
Heydeln, is that you?
（ハイデルン）
生きているとは思わなかったぞ。
I didn't think you were still alive!
（バーレン）
貴様こそ。　この死に損ないが。
Same to you!
（バーレン　ハイデルン）ははははっ。
（ドメル）ゴルニ戦役以来だな。
It's been since the Gorni Campaign.
Indeed.
（バーレン）そうなりますかな。
艦は古く　兵は幼い。
We have old ships and young men. Can you do this?
やれるか？
兵は　戦場で→
You were the one who said that a soldier comes of age on the battlefield.
一人前になると言われたのは
閣下でしたな。
（ドメル）ふん。　頼むぞ。
（バーレン）ザー・ベルク！
I'm counting on you.
Zar Belk!
Attention!
（ハイニ）気を～つけぇ～！
（ドメル）フラーケン
また　貴様の手を借りる。
Flakken, I'll need your help once more.
（フラーケン）
ふっ。　バレラスは　空気が悪い。→
The air in Baleras is horrible.
I'd jump at the chance.
願ってもないです。
（ドメル）頼むぞ。
（バーガー）ん？
I'm counting on you.
A squad of second-class Garmillas subjects?
（ゲットー）２等ガミラスの部隊か。
（クライツェ）惑星ザルツの義勇兵だ。
Volunteers from Planet Zaltz.
（バーガー）占領地の人間かよ。
From a conquered territory?
（ハイデルン）
シュルツと同じ星の出身者です。
They're from the same planet as Schultz.
We are the 442nd Special Platoon, Specialized Warfare Group B.
（ゲルト）Ｂ特殊戦群所属
第４４２特務小隊であります。
I have an extremely important mission for you. You're aware of it, correct?
諸君には　極めて重要な任務を→
任せることになる。
承知しているな？
We will do all we can for Garmillas.
（ゲルト）ガミラスのため
全力を尽くします。
（バーガー）
はっ！　信用できるか怪しいもんだ。
I'm not sure we can trust them.
（ハイニ）おっ？　おっ？
（ノラン）♪♪　青き花咲く大地
Our noble home,
（３人）♪♪　気高き我が故郷よ
planet where the blue flowers blossom.
Sing a song of joy!
（３人）♪♪　響け歓喜の歌
（一同）♪♪　神の加護は
May god's grace always be with us.
（一同）♪♪　我らと共にあり続けん
（一同）♪♪　ガーレ！　ガミロン！
Ghale Garmillon! Hail to the victory of our home.
（一同）♪♪　讃えよ　祖国の勝利を！
Regular Wave Motion Gun inspection is complete.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）
波動砲　定期点検　終了。→
All responsible personnel should report to Weapons Officer.
担当員は　砲雷長に検査報告。
≫（南部）整備は　怠るなよ。→
Keep this thing in good shape.
No matter how often the Garmillans show up,
ガミラスが何度来たって
波動砲があれば　ヤマトは無敵さ。
the Yamato is invincible so long as we have this.
あれ？　艦長。
何か御用ですか？
Oh!
Captain...
Do you need something?
No, it's nothing.
いや　なんでもない。
≫シューン（ドアの音）
どうしたんだ？
さあ？
What's wrong with him?
No idea...
ん？
その奥にあるものは→
What lies back there is a tool of war.
戦うためのもの。
Wave Motion Energy is not a weapon.
波動エネルギーは　武器ではない。
武器にしてはいけない。
You mustn't make it a weapon.
It is to enable you to cross the stars.
あれは　星を渡るためのもの。
The plans you received a year ago were to take you to Iscandar.
１年前
あなたたちに渡した設計図は→
イスカンダルへ来るためのもの。
During our journey of 168,000 light years, we required protection from Garmillas.
１６万８０００光年を
旅する我々には→
ガミラスから
身を守る武器が必要だった。
And therefore, Sanada created it.
（百合亜）
そして　作ってしまった…　真田が。
Crime
&
Punishment
（百合亜）
それでは　ガミラスと同じ。→
But that makes you no different from the Garmillans.
Is the wave motion gun truly only for your protection?
波動砲は
本当に　身を守るためだけのもの？
信じてほしい　我々を。
I'd like for you to believe in us.
Why...
（百合亜）なぜ　尋ねないのかな？
Why not ask me?
Why we didn't bring you
どうして　波動エンジンではなく
コスモリバースを→
the Cosmo Reverser directly, rather than the Wave Motion Engine?
直接　持ってきては
くれなかったのだ…　と。
Perhaps we are being tested.
我々は
試されているのかもしれない→
By you... By your people.
あなたに…　あなたたちに。
I simply observe.
私はただ　観察するだけ。
判断するのは→
It is my sister Starsha's job to decide.
スターシャ姉様の務め。
Then I hope you'll watch carefully.
では　その目で
全てを見届けていただきたい。
ヤマトが…　いや→
And see if the Yamato...
No, whether humanity is worth saving.
人類が　救うにたりうる
存在なのかどうかを。
Once the weapons are aboard the Domelaze
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）ドメラーズへの
兵装設置を完了しだい→
7th Maintenance Company is to begin loading fighters onto the Balgrey.
第７整備中隊は
バルグレイに対し→
艦上機の搭載作業準備に入れ。
A top-secret prototype... No less.
（タラン）最高機密の試作兵器。→
まったく…
兵器開発局を説き伏せるのは→
It wasn't easy convincing Weapons Research.
ひと苦労だったぞ。
（ドメル）感謝してます。
I'm grateful.
It's fine... I'm accustomed to your requests.
（タラン）まあいいさ。
君のわがままには慣れている。→
But why would you need such a thing?
しかし　あんなものまで
一体　なんに使うつもりだ？
こいつは
小惑星鉱山用の特殊削岩弾だろ？
Isn't this a drill for asteroid mining? Why load it as a bomb?
爆装して　どうするつもりなんだ？
さあな。
上の考えることは分からんよ。
Who knows? I'll never understand the higher-ups.
≪おい　どうなってる!?
（メルダ）ん？
中佐殿！
なんだ!?　貴様ら！
- Lieutenant Brigadier!
- What are you doing with him?!
（メルダ）あっ！
（ヘルダー）騒ぐな。→
Stay calm.
I've done nothing to make them arrest me. They'll see that when they investigate.
私は　拘束されるようなことは
何もしていない。→
調べれば分かることだ。
ヘルダー中佐！　あっ…。
Lieutenant Brigadier Helder!
やめろ！
中佐殿！
- Sir!
- Lieutenant Brigadier Helder!
あっ！
Damn you!
親衛隊め！
中佐殿！
（ドルメン）これが　我々が
命懸けで守ろうとしている→
This is what's really happening in the home we're risking our lives to protect.
祖国の実情だ。
（メルダ）貴様たちは？
Who are you guys?
Lower Storm Leader Melda Ditz, right?
（ドルメン）
メルダ・ディッツ少尉ですね？
（真田）大マゼランの先端に位置する
このタランチュラ星雲は→
The Tarantula Nebula, at the edge of the Large Magellanic Cloud,
濃密な星間物質や　イオンの嵐が→
is filled with interstellar medium and ion storms.
吹き荒れる環境になっている。
These seven stars make up the nebula.
（島）
星雲を形成する　この７つの恒星→
For convenience, we'll call them the Rainbow Cluster.
便宜上　七色星団と呼びますが→
そこを突破するのが
最短コースとなります。
Heading through this is our fastest course.
But degenerate stars comprise this cluster, and it's also filled with relativistic jets.
ですが
縮退星で構成される　この星団は→
宇宙ジェットの噴出も
観測される→
最も危険な宙域でもあるわけです。
It is the most dangerous area along our course.
We're already seeing issues with the Cosmo Radar.
すでに　コスモレーダーに
障害が出はじめています。
Can't the warp get us through?
（南部）
ワープで回避できないのか？
Even at maximum warp, we wouldn't make it through. It's too big.
（太田）最大ワープでも
飛び越えられないよ。→
全体領域が広すぎる。
んん…
突破するのは難しそうだな。
It'll be difficult to get through.
Yes, so I've charted a course around it.
ああ。　そこで
迂回するコースを策定した。
This is the course we believe the Yamato will take on their way to Salezar.
（ゲットー）ヤマトが　サレザーに
向かうと想定した場合の→
予想される航路だ。
Then the quickest route is through the Rainbow Cluster?
（クライツェ）最短コースは　七色星団か。
Heading through that would be suicide. They aren't that stupid.
（バーガー）こんな難所を通るなんて
自殺行為だ。→
ヤツらも　バカじゃないさ。
（ゲットー）七色星団を→
If they plan to avoid the Rainbow Cluster, that doesn't leave many routes.
回避するとなると
取れるコースは限られてくるな。
いや　バラン星で　一歩
先んずることができたといって→
No...
Even if we did gain a step on them at Balun,
navigating around would give the enemy time to mount a counterattack.
我々が　迂回コースをたどれば
それが油断となり→
相手に
反撃の時間を与えることとなる。
The enemy is also unlikely to expect us to go through a dangerous area like this.
（真田）この危険な宙域を
我々が突破するとは→
敵も　考え難いでしょう。
うむ。
Yes. We will continue through the Rainbow Cluster, to Iscandar.
本艦は　七色星団を抜け
イスカンダルを目指す。
星団通過中は
第一種戦闘態勢を維持。
As we travel through the cluster, we will maintain alert status
and carefully monitor anti-air scanners.
対空警戒を厳とせよ。
9 minutes to warp
Balgrey ready to launch.
（通信）バルグレイ　発進準備　完了。
Lambea ready to launch.
（通信）ランベア　発進準備　完了。
Schderg ready to launch.
（通信）シュデルグ　発進準備　完了。
Daurold ready to launch.
（通信）ダロルド　発進準備　完了。
All ships ready to launch.
（ハイデルン）全艦　発進準備　完了。
Launch all ships.
全艦　発進せよ！
（航宙士）
艦隊　第２バレラス　通過します。
The fleet is passing Second Baleras.
I will now announce our course.
これより
全艦に　針路を通達する。→
Course 728. Our destination is the Rainbow Cluster.
（通信）
コース７２８。　目標　七色星団。
七色星団？
マジかよ…。
The Rainbow Cluster?
Seriously?
（クライツェ）ふん。
ふっ。
But will they really come through such a dangerous area?
（ハイデルン）しかし　本当に
この難所にやってくるでしょうか？
（ドメル）彼らは来る。
They will come.
If the captain of the Yamato is the man I think him to be,
ヤマトの艦長が
私の思ったとおりの男なら→
they will come through the Rainbow Cluster.
必ず　七色星団を突き進んでくる。
（一同）うわぁ～！
電離ガス　濃度　高い！
High-density ionized gas!
くっ…　舵を　手動に移行！
S-Switching helm to manual!
Radar and sensors aren't working correctly.
（西条）レーダー　センサーともに
感度よくない。→
Switching to optic mode.
光学モードに切り替える。
So we'll have to rely on optic mode?
頼りは　光学モードだけか。
これじゃ　大昔の洋上艦だな。
We're like an old sailing ship.
≪もし敵が
あのときの指揮官だったら…≫
If the enemy is the commander we faced before...
（フラーケン）上は大荒れだぞ　ハイニ。
（ハイニ）そいつぁいい。
There's a storm up there, Heyni.
Sounds good!
Ship detected at nine o'clock.
（ソナー士）感あり。　９時の方角。
There it is.
（フラーケン）いたな。
Message from the Hound! The sheep has entered the lost forest.
（通信士）猟犬より入電
「羊は　迷いの森に入った」。
You were right.
（ハイデルン）読みが当たりましたな。
Yes.
ああ。
これより　作戦行動に移る。
We will commence the operation.
Fighter Group 1, prepare for launch.
（ヴォック）
第一次攻撃隊　発艦準備に入れ。
Attention all decks: First Attack Force, prepare for launch.
（ゲットー）艦長　あとを頼みます。
Captain, I'll count on you for the rest.
ご武運を　少佐。
Good luck, Rear Brigadier.
（航宙士）
作戦宙域まで　あと７０ゲック。
70 gek to the operation area.
（小橋・通信）こんな荒れた海で
仕掛けてくるかな？→
Will they attack in rough seas like these?
今回は　篠さんもいないし…。
（大工原・通信）ビビるな　小橋。
Shino isn't with us this time.
Don't be so scared, Kobashi.
（小橋・通信）ビビってない！
（大工原）安心しろ。→
I'm not scared!
Don't worry.
何かあったら　あいつらの分も
俺が働いてやるって。
If anything happens, I'll work hard enough to make up for their part.
I'll hold you to that, Daikuhara.
（沢村）言いますねぇ　大工原の旦那。
（加藤・通信）無駄口をたたくな→
Keep quiet, Sawamura.
沢村！
おっと…。
If they attack under these conditions, only we can protect the Yamato.
（加藤・通信）
この状況下で仕掛けられたら→
ヤマトを守れるのは俺たちだけだ。
（沢村・通信）でも→
But aren't we leaving the missus?
お嬢は　置いてくんですよね？
（加藤・通信）ああ。→
Yeah, she's our ace in the hole.
あいつは　切り札だからな。
（伊東）
宇宙人なんか信じるな。
Don't trust aliens. If you do, we'll all die... We'll all die!
信じたら　みんな死ぬ。
死んじまうんだ！
（太田）乱流層を突破。
Breaking through turbulence layer!
ふぅ～。
ここは　凪いだ海だな。
Seas are calm out here.
Something on radar!
レーダーに感。
敵攻撃機と思われる編隊。
Enemy fighter formation. Twenty-seven light seconds away.
距離２７光秒。
Battle stations!
総員　配置に着け！
All crew to battle stations. Fighter Group, launch immediately!
総員　戦闘配置！
航空隊は　直ちに出撃せよ。
≫ウィン　ウィン　ウィン…（警報）
They're coming... And bringing the war with them.
彼らは来た…　戦いと共に。
One hundred. Kato... Launching!
（加藤）１００　加藤　発艦する。
（西条）航空隊　全機発艦。
All fighters have launched!
Episode 19: They're Coming!
少しずつ色を変える
空を二人眺めてた
未来の約束もないまま
繋いだ手握り返した
終りにしたほうがいいって
頭でわかっても
心が言うことをきかなくて
あなたをなくしたら
明日に何を思えばいい？
教えてよ
愛してるって言わないで
またつらくなってしまうから
今はただ　何も言わずに
夕日が姿消すまで　そばにいて
A pack of wolves descends. An invisible hunting dog lurks in the shadows, ready to strike.
The battle begins in a rainbow sky. The time has come to decide the final victor.
This battle is a test that must be passed.
Next time: Under a Rainbow Sun.
There are 245 days left before humanity is extinct.
全艦に達する。　本艦は　これより→
限定「ヤマト」グッズの
プレゼントを行う。
表示中の番号に　電話を→
かけるだけで　応募は完了する。
応募の殺到が予測されるが→
当選は　たった５名だ。
視聴者からすれば
これは→
千載一遇の好機だ。
全艦→
第一種応募受け付け態勢
発令。
受け～付けぇ　始め！
今日正午過ぎ、宮城県沖を震源と
する
最大震度５強の強い地震があった
東日本大震災の余震と見られ、
宮城県内で４人がケガをした。
今日午後０時２８分頃、